Middle Eastern country. This is
something we did literally every single
day, usually multiple times a day. And
what we do is we set up a day of
briefings, they get a photo op with the
director, you know, shaking hands, we
exchange gifts, and we take them out to
a fancy dinner at night. So, these guys,
they're all mid-level, like majors and
lieutenant colonels.
>> So, it's a lot of [__]
>> Yeah, there's a lot of it, a lot, yes.
So, I set up a day of briefings, and I I
went to see this kid, young guy, 20s,
uh that was covering Al-Qaeda, and I
said, "Can you come and just talk to
these guys about Al-Qaeda for an hour?"
He said, "Yes."
So, it came time for his briefing, but
instead of him coming,
the director of counterterrorism comes,
Cofer Black,
uh later Ambassador Cofer Black, and he
comes
>> From which country?
>> Uh
you the
>> Oh, from the US.
>> Yeah, yeah. He was our director
>> So, he showed up.
>> Cofer shows up with the director of
operations from the Osama bin Laden
unit.
And um and I jumped [clears throat] up.
I was I was like, "Oh, uh gentlemen," I
said, "this is This is Cofer Black. He's
the director of counterterrorism for the
entire
American intelligence community."
>> And you were working in counterterrorism
at the time. Got it.
>> And so, he came in and and sat down, and
he was very, very serious.
He said, uh "Something terrible is going
to happen. We don't know exactly when or
exactly where, but we know it's going to
be an attack on a scale that we've never
seen before." He said, "We're picking up
chatter from the Al-Qaeda training
camps, where camp commanders are on the
phone with their students, and they're
crying and telling them, 'I'll see you
in paradise.'" We're hearing code words
for a massive attack, "The honey
salesman is coming with vast quantities
of honey, or there's going to be a huge
wedding, or a huge football game." And
he said, "We know that they're planning
an enormous attack. We just don't know
when or where." And he said, "I'm
begging you, if you have any sources
inside Al-Qaeda, please help us." They
just sat there and looked at him.
Nothing. So, at the end of the day, I
was not working on Al-Qaeda at the time.
I later, weeks later, became the chief
of uh
counterintelligence in the Osama bin
Laden unit.
And so,
I went to his office at at the end of
the day before I took those guys to
dinner, and I said, "Koffer, I got to
tell you,
you shocked me with that briefing today.
Was that just for them, or were you
serious?" He said, "Oh, I was deadly
serious. Something terrible is going to
happen." And then on September 11th,
there it was. He and I were supposed to
go to the White House that morning. We
had a meeting with Condoleezza Rice, who
was the National Security Advisor at the
time, on an issue that's so stupid now,
I'm almost embarrassed to tell you what
it is.
It was about a a book that was being
printed by the Government Printing
Office, this minor governmental agency
called
Greece, Turkey, Cyprus. No, it was
called Foreign Affairs of the United
States, Greece, Turkey, Cyprus, 1949 to
1967. Literally, nobody's going to read
this book.
>> Nobody, I was going to tell you that.
Nobody's going to read it.
>> Literally, nobody.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's like a thousand pages long.
>> That's money laundering.
>> And it had the names of three CIA
sources who were still alive.
And we've got this obscure law in the
United States that if the government
outs a CIA source, we have to offer the
source citizenship. These guys are like
and 97 years old. They're not going to
They don't care.
>> Right.
>> Nobody's going to read the book anyway.
So, um
we were going to go down there and ask
her just pull those pages out of the out
of the book, you know? Nobody's going to
miss it. Nobody's going to read it
anyhow. Just pull the pages out or
redact the names or whatever.
But, I went up to tell him that the car
was ready, and the secretary's got a
little TV on her desk, and the World
Trade Center's on fire. I said, "What
happened to World Trade Center?"
She said a plane flew into it. And I go,
cuz I'm a genius, I said, "You know,
that happened once before in 1930. A
bomber flew into the Empire State
Building, but it was like pouring rain
and fog. I said, "It's so crystal clear
today. How can you not see that you're
flying into the World Trade Center?" And
just as I spoke the words, the second
plane hit.
And then she turned and she said, "Did
you see that or did I imagine it?"
And it's like, uh,
everything is going to go to [__] now.
>> And And at this point you're already
working in counterterrorism, yeah?
>> Well, I was already in counterterrorism,
but I was working on a group See, again,
I'm embarrassed to even say it. I was
working in a group that was targeting
European communist terrorists like
Carlos the Jackal,
who nobody remembers now. He was the
Osama bin Laden of the '70s. Nobody
remembers who in the world he was.
>> Really?
>> Yeah, Carlos the Jackal.
>> Bring him up.
>> There he is.
>> Wow, he looks suave, huh?
>> He was Venezuelan, Ilich Ramírez
Sánchez.
>> Mhm.
>> Listen to the balls this guy had.
OPEC had an oil ministers meeting,
right?
So, the ministers
>> And for those who don't know what OPEC
is, it's the Organization of Petroleum
Exporting Countries. So, um, it's
basically like your oil kind of,
um, commission.
>> yeah.
>> Right?
>> Yeah. It's a
the,
what do you call it? The, cartel. It's
an oil cartel.
>> So,
he and his gang of terrorists
raided the OPEC oil ministers meeting in
Vienna, Austria and kidnapped every
single minister of oil.
They killed three people, says there.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> He and he demanded a plane, flew
everybody to Libya, took his
billion-dollar ransom that they gave
him, and then let everybody go.
>> Wow.
So, he was just trying to get a bag,
really, huh?
>> Oh, yeah, and he was good at it. And
then he was so good at it, he set up
terrorist training camps in Libya and
Lebanon, and he trained the IRA, the
Irish Republican Army. He trained
Greece's Revolutionary Organization 17
November, the Red Brigades, the Action
Direct, the
>> Why did he feel so convicted to to do
this sort of behavior?
>> He was a true believing communist.
And he just wanted to bring down the
West.
>> Uh-huh.
Interesting.
>> Yeah.
>> But take me back. So, it's like you guys
hear that something's going to happen.
>> Something terrible's going to happen.
>> But what do you do at that point?
>> Well, see, that's the key. What do you
do? We We didn't know what to do. So,
we're going to the, you know,
Jordanians, the Egyptians, the Saudis,
the this one, and that one. And they're
like, "We We don't know what's going
on." Well, as it turned out, that wasn't
true.
Um
almost all the hijackers What Was it 17
16 or 17 of the hijackers came from
Saudi Arabia.
>> right?
>> And we know that the Saudi ambassador to
the United States at the time, Prince
Bandar bin Sultan al-Saud, his wife
transferred $50,000 from her personal
bank account to the hijackers.
What are we supposed to make of that?
>> Yeah, sometimes you got to get your girl
to Venmo if you need to get it, you know
what I'm saying?
>> Seriously, you know, the only time I
ever saw George Tenet, who was the CIA
director at the time, the only time I
ever saw George completely lose his [__]
was in a meeting with Prince Bandar.
He said,
"If we don't start getting help from the
Saudi government
on this case, we're going to start
killing people, a lot of people, and
some of them are going to be named
al-Saud."
I go out to Pakistan as the chief of
counterterrorism operations there in
January of '02. So, it's still fresh.
We're bombing Tora Bora. All these
al-Qaeda people are trying to get out of
Afghanistan, cross into into Pakistan.
And my job was then to catch them when
they came into Pakistan.
>> what? We're bombing We're bombing which
country?
>> Afghanistan.
>> Afghanistan, right? But there was Why
were we looking for al-Qaeda in
Afghanistan?
>> That's where they were living, all of
them. They launched 9/11 from
Afghanistan. Got it. At least
theoretically, the ideas came when they
were in Afghanistan.
>> Because from the American like
population it always felt like we never
went after Saudi Arabia. That's what it
felt like.
>> Yeah. And we should have.
>> But if you Didn't you know that?
>> We did not. We suspected, but we didn't
have There was no smoking gun. So,
that's what I'm getting to. We catch Abu
Zubaydah, Zayn al-Abidin Muhammad
Husayn. Abu Zubaydah, who we believed at
the time was
>> you were having a stroke for a second
there.
>> no. His name
>> No, I'm just joking. That was a joke.
>> The profession I know. The profession of
faith La ilaha illallah Muhammad Rasul
Allah every day of my
>> people that are stroking out and if you
don't tap in with them, they'll just
keep going.
>> Oh, jeez.
>> You know? And they They never buy a
vowel and then they just [__] tap
out, you know?
>> terrible. So, you guys were doing this
guy?
>> for him.
>> Oh, bro.
>> And we catch him.
>> This dude is a [__] mumble rapper, I
think. Go on.
>> He We were on him for 6 weeks we chased
him. Some days we'd bust down the door
and there's like a warm meal and a
half-lit cigarette still on the table.
We're like, "Dang it, with 15 minutes we
could have gotten him."
Some days we were a day or two behind.
So, he knew we were after him. He knew
we were chasing him all over the
freaking country.
And
we catch him.
In late March 2002 in Faisalabad,
Pakistan.
So,
we also confiscated his
diary. This This led to a huge fight
between the FBI and the CIA. Huge. And
the CIA was right and the FBI was wrong.
But, um
the The fight was What? We had We had
captured his diary.
So, I'm sitting here
>> sounds so suspect that he has a diary.
>> It was more than a diary, though.
>> But, even though, you know what I'm
saying? Like as a regular person
>> have terrorism stuff in it.